so hello everyone um I just thought that
it might be a good idea to make a little
video recording and share it in the
group to give you a sense of how things
are emerging here in body Chara and
Columbia where we are as it relates to
everything we've discussed in this study
group because right now in the midst of
this time when there are so many
disruptions to people's normal routines
there are opportunities to co-create
different social arrangements as they
relate to extractive and destructive
activities that people were complicit in
through no fault of their own by
participating in the dominant economy
and now they're opening up to new
possibilities and I wanted to just tell
you a little bit about what's happening
here in party chara because I think we
can learn a lot from it so just to give
you a brief context we're in the
northern Andes of Colombia in a place
that's a tropical dry forest so that
means that it rains for about three
months of the year and then there's an
extended dry season for about nine
months of the year and this is a place
as you've probably gathered from other
posts that has at extreme deforestation
has problems with water quality and
water scarcity but at the same time has
a very rich in deep cultural history of
campesino culture where the campesinos
are farmers who live out in the
countryside growing their own food and a
lot of them have already been bringing
their vegetables and their produce into
town to sell in some of the local shops
so that there is a bit of a local food
system that's very well integrated in
this place what I want to share
specifically right now is something
that's happened in the last three days
when a group was created on what's up
and for those of you who don't know
what's up is the most common
communication tool used across Latin
America so people organize themselves
into groups and its really how most
information gets shared but a whatsup
group was created around discussions for
community resilience the idea being that
the people organizing this group would
like to initiate and facilitate the
the process of transformation and the
reason that chosen three months is that
right now we're entering into a lockdown
as it relates to the corona virus
pandemic trying to stop the spread of
the disease which is having a lot of
economic effects immediately but we also
know from the projections of future
change in many countries around the
world that about a month from now there
will begin to be chronic and persistent
global system problems as all of the
different countries have been locking
down and shutting down transport and the
mobility of people and things like this
so we're also in a time where we're
about to begin the rainy season and so
we're gonna have a very limited window
of time for two to three months where we
could build systems for water retention
and direct them into food production to
create food security during the nine to
ten months of dry season afterwards and
about three months from now as when that
rainy season is likely to end because
it's just about to begin
so we have about three months to do as
much as we can to transform this system
and what's happening is a group of
facilitators have created their own
whatsup group to discuss processes and
tools in what we're learning as we go to
direct into the main community
resilience group as well as other
focused groups that are looking at food
security for one group education because
all of the kids are out of school and
there's a need to learn new skills this
is an education focus and then the third
primary focus right now is alternative
economic models so for example there's
an activity going going on in the third
group to map out who are the local
people that produce food and then
connect them to small clusters of
families that become group buyers of
that food so it might be that four or
five families agreed to buy the yuca
plant from one farmer or four or five
families might agree to buy all the eggs
from one farmer to make it very
efficient to distribute food to people
and create stable food security but also
this is a mapping process so we can
begin to see at the landscape scale what
are the capabilities for food production
so this is all happening emergently it's
messy there's a lot of confusion as the
official Colombian government is
initiating a three-week long quarantine
obligating people to remain in their
homes and so we're bringing together the
collective knowledge of this place
through self-organizing activities and I
just want to share this with you to give
you a sense that while it's important to
take care of our own families to limit
the contagion effects of spreading the
disease as it's having as other
consequences the corona virus as its own
phenomenon there's also a tremendous
opportunity to cultivate the conditions
for collective intelligence to
understand what's happening across an
entire region in our case the landscape
of deforested land and all of the people
who have different kinds of food
production water storage skills and
knowledge that are relevant to community
resilience and my wife and I have
bicycles
so we've my wife just in the food group
offered to collect food from producers
on our bicycles and deliberate other
people's homes similarly there's a group
that is coordinating a time of day where
people do a movement meditation in their
homes to create solidarity between
people and they'll use what's up to
share their experience of doing body
movements together and meditating about
how to have psychological health and
well-being and there are actually a lot
of other activities happening it's a
very dynamic and generative time but I
want to share this with you to give you
a feel for what is possible as old
routines break down and new patterns
with foresight and good facilitation new
patterns can emerge so that's what's
happening here and I just wanted to show
that with you let's have a conversation
about it
um let's all become better regenerators
of our communities of ourselves and our
families and of the landscapes that we
depend upon for survival